Oh my gosh, you guys have awesome people. Awesome people. Do I need to flip a switch, or are we good to go? I can't see them in the back. Okay. I'm flipping it the other way. Woo! All right. Yeah, we had a few technical difficulties yesterday, but not enough to, like, you know, dampen the Holy Spirit because,
he's good at technical difficulties. Yeah, he is. I just gotta say, campus community church, thank you for such an amazing welcome. I've had a great time this weekend. Melissa, thank you for dragging me here. This man emailed me every day for three years.
I've never eaten in my entire life at the most beautiful table I've ever seen. I'm going home completely intimidated and convinced that I have never actually been a hostess, ever, ever, ever. And Ryan and Sam and Nick and Cory and Mark, all of your regional pastors, yeah, I'm like, really kidding me.
Okay, so I'm about to say something to you that I would never say to my classes. Are you ready? Pull out your phone. And as we pull out a phone, because I'm a professor, we're going to launch with a quiz. I have never done this before. Ryan has never done this before. We have no idea if this is going to work, but we're going to give it a shot.
So, as you pull out your phone and pull up your QR code, we have got a sequence of questions to ask you. Do you have it on your phone? Is it there? Do you see it? All right. So, who wrote the book of Psalms? How many books are in the book of Psalms? When was the book of Psalms written? And how many different kinds of Psalms are in the book of Psalms? Go.
Oh, yes. Yeah, I will. First, I'm putting the package in. All right. I hope you all are doing better than I'm doing up here.
Where's the Jeopardy music? Do, do, do, do. Do, do, do. Okay, okay. How are we doing? Yeah? Are we done? Not yet? Not yet? Or as I would say in intro to Old Testament, does anyone need any more time? Yes.
These guys over here are done. What's wrong with those people over there?
All right, anyone need more time? Okay, we're there, we're there. Dave, are we going to be able to show results on the screen? Are we going to be able to do it? Okay, first question.
Who wrote the Book of Psalms? You were given, ooh, look at this. Okay, the options were Moses, David, Solomon, He-Man the Ephraite.
Okay, I got to tell you, he's my favorite. And I can tell you for your eight-year-old son, He-Man is his favorite as well.
But y'all are absolutely right. It is all of the above. Give yourselves a hand.
Okay, King David actually has 73 Psalms attributed to him. And so we speak of David as the sweet singer of Israel.
But reality is, we don't know if La David, meaning belonging to David, if that means he wrote them, they were dedicated to them,
they're a part of his collection, or they're just on his playlist. Okay? So we've got David, we've got Moses, Solomon,
Asaph, the sons of Korah, who are basically your worship team coming out of the temple, He-Man, Ethan,
all of these guys are responsible, and their names are listed. Okay? So even though our New Testament
will talk about the book of Psalms as David's book, the New Testament knows perfectly well
that all of the above is the correct answer. All right, how many books are in the book of Psalms?
How you guys did this? All right, one, three, five. Okay, you thought that that would work well
because it worked on the first question. And I just want you to know that I have written
more than one exam. And I know that if you let the same letter be the right answer each time,
the guy in the back with the baseball cap will figure that out really fast. So I am sorry to say that number five
is the correct answer. Yeah, come on. So there are five books in the book of Psalms. How does that work?
Well, the idea is that the book of Psalms is a collection that was collected for a very long time and distilled into five.
Hmm. Ryan, help me out with this. Five books. Five books. What other collection do we have in the Old Testament? Five.
Pentateuch. Yes. All right. The Pentateuch. So what that tells us is more than likely the final collection happened after the Pentateuch was collected as five books.
So the final collection is probably after the exile. Interesting, isn't it? And if you look in your Bibles between Psalm 41 and 42, and I know you're a Bible-caring church, you will see that the biblical author actually tells you book two.
And that's not the NIV translation committee. That is the original authors. Okay. When was the book of Psalms written? How'd you guys do on that?
Oh, we're getting a lot of all of the above going on here. I did tell you about the guy in the back with the baseball cap, right?
Okay. So the answer is indeed all of the above. Thank you. The first Psalm you've got in your Bible is actually the Song of the Sea in Exodus 15.
Now, it didn't wind up in the book of Psalms because it was already in the book of Exodus, but this collection spans their entire experience.
So as you start thinking about the book of Psalms, you should be thinking Chris Tomlin's How Great Is Our God, The Essential Collection. You get it?
That these songs run all the way from the beginning of their experience to the end, or perhaps the very best of Hillsong Live, 2010, or the best of Maverick City Music, which is now on a playlist, not an album.
Okay, how many different kinds of Psalms are in the Book of Psalms? How'd you go for that one? Yeah, and absolutely right.
This is the right answer to, oh, so many questions of biblical scholarship. I made my 19-year-old take this test before I gave it to you, and she's like, "Mom, if there's anything I've learned from you, living with you for 19 years, scholars are still arguing about it."
Yeah, so we've got hymns, we've got laments, community laments, individual laments, songs of ascent, royal psalms. We've got the song they always use when they're putting the son of David on the throne. That's Psalm 2, by the way, which is quoted at David's baptism, at Jesus' baptism, by the way.
We've got all this different sorts of genre included because the Book of Psalms is supposed to be a gift, a gift to the congregation of God's people
that assists God's people in worship. So, first of all, give yourselves a hand. You did absolutely awesome. Yeah. I think you need more enthusiasm about that. Woohoo! Yeah, yeah. And I want to know if there is anyone in the room that doesn't have the word reverend in front of their name, who got everything right. Oh, my gosh. Okay, I'm going over here, and we have prizes. Oh, yes, we do. And the study
guide for the Book of Psalms come grab your prize. Oh, yeah? Aren't you so glad that... Woohoo! Woohoo! Okay. So, as we think about the Book of Psalms, we need to be thinking about a collection, a culled collection, yeah, gathered for over a thousand years to facilitate the worship of the people of God in first the tabernacle and then the temple. Your Book of Psalms is the essential collection.
You need to know that there are dozens of authors in the mix. They began collecting these prayers and liturgies, and if you're Anglican, collect as early as the days of the Exodus, and they kept collecting them all the way through the return from the exile. And whereas you and I would be tempted to think that every psalm that was written wound up in the collection, the news is there are 150 psalms in your collection, but the Dead Sea Scrolls will tell us that David
David himself wrote 3,600. 150? 3,600. In other words, not every psalm written made the cut, yeah? The 150 you have are the best. And it's kind of like thinking about Charles Wesley, yeah? Do you know how many songs that poor man wrote? 6,500. 6,500 up from the grave he arose is his, yeah?
Oh, how can it be, is his good old Wesley man. The only problem with Charles Wesley is he only had three tunes. So I'm really grateful for the worship teams that kind of upgrade. All right, so with my classes, I think it's really helpful to talk about the Book of Psalms as the hymn book of ancient Israel. Now you guys, I can tell, have kind of abandoned the hymn book thing. You got the slide thing going. But you all know what a hymn book is.
And so just like our hymn books are an essential collection that reflects generations of worshipers, running from Martin Luther to Charles Wesley, Fanny Crosby, Chris Tomlin, that we've got baptism, communion, marriage, graveside services, all tucked into that one book, that's your Book of Psalms. And in that book, what you see is a book that reflects our past, our present, and our future.
And I am so glad that your pastor put up on the screen what Athanasius, the church father, had to say about this book. Whereas most of Scripture speaks to us, the Psalms speak for us. And so when you find yourself in that dark night of the soul, open up that book. It's the only book in the Bible designed for you to do this. Only one. And you pick that Psalm.
And you let your forefathers in the faith pray for you. And they will. They will. Okay. So let's get to our Psalm 4 this morning. Our text is the most well-worn and well-loved Psalm in your Old Testament. Psalm 23, "The Lord is my shepherd." It is a Psalm of David, written by or dedicated to, we're not sure. But the sentiments that it communicates, well, I would argue that they are not only the sentiments of David,
sentiments that he was forced to struggle with over and over and over again as he attempted to serve the kingdom, to build the kingdom. But they are the sentiments of every person sitting in this room at some point in time in our lives. This is the universal human experience. What are the agonies at hand as this Psalm is put to paper, or perhaps, you know, leather, hard clay?
The questions are this: is there anyone out there who's got my back? Anyone out there who's got my back? Am I going to make it through this, be it a threat, fear, anxiety, a diagnosis that has rocked you to the core of your being? Am I going to make it through this? Is God paying attention?
Now, by genre, Psalm 23 is a hymn of confidence. I kind of like that. And it rests on our souls the way a warm cup of chamomile tea, in that perfect mug that your grandmother gave you, sits in our hands at the end of a very long and difficult day. As we're sitting on the back patio, and everybody else is inside, and we know that God's got this.
That's Psalm 23. So my ambition this morning is to make what is old new, what is familiar unfamiliar, and to thereby remind both of us, you and me, yeah, that the Lord is my shepherd. To remind both you and me who I am and whose I am. Because the Lord is indeed my shepherd, and as Psalm 95:7
likes to say it, you and I, we're the sheep of His hand. So let's get started, shall you? Shall we? Yes. All of us know at least some of the words of Psalm 23, "The Lord is my shepherd, I shall not wad." All of us know that Jesus claims to be the good shepherd. A lot of us know that Philip Keller has written a killer devotional about sheep and shepherds, but very few of us know why the image of shepherd with his sheep is so prevalent in our Bibles, and so regularly
frequents our faith lives. Let's take George Adam Smith, for example. Now Smith was a Scottish theologian, who back in 1880 took his horse, his journals, canteen, and of course his faithful sidekick, and decided to head over to Israel-Palestine in order to map out the entire country. And he did this without a four-wheel drive, without sunblock, air conditioning,
or a Visa card. He's still a bit of a legend in my field. And this is what Smith had to say about the real-life shepherds that he met on every hill and dell in the Holy Land. The quote:
"On some high moor, across which at night hyenas howl. When you meet him, sleepless, farsighted, weather-beaten, armed, and leaning on his staff,
looking out over his scattered sheep, every one of them on his heart, you understand why the shepherd of Judea sprang to the front in his people's history,
why they gave his name to their king and they made him the symbol of providence, and why Christ took him as the type of self-sacrifice."
Yeah. Not bad for a theologian. Not bad for an academic, actually, is what I want to say. Yeah? Beautiful. Now, I know that
when you all think of sheep, you are thinking of these little beauties with their cute little black faces and overall fluffiness. Yeah?
That's a beautiful image, isn't it? This is Inverkip, Scotland. Once in my life, I want to live in a town named Inverkip.
I mean, come on. And this is last summer when I dragged my daughters with me to the NIV meetings, and where the amazing Mark and Sharon Rogers,
YWAM missionaries, took us on this beautiful evening hike, which in Scotland in June is like at 10 o'clock at night. Yeah?
And we went out and ate tea and cakes and interacted with all of those cute little fluffy sheep, and we had a blast.
But here's the deal. This isn't the kind of sheep or the kind of sheep terrain that we're talking about when we talk about Psalm 23.
Rather, this is the kind of terrain that you're talking about.
You're looking at my friend and colleague, a professor of archaeology and biblical studies, Ralph Hawkins at Averitt University and his crew,
and they are busy digging at Kirbit al-Mastra. It's in the Jordan Valley. It's north of Jericho.
But you see those rocks in the background? Or you think they're rocks? Well, those rocks are moving, ladies and gentlemen,
because those rocks are actually sheep and goats.
And this kind of terrain that you're looking at is absolutely familiar to our heroes who are in the Bible.
But it's not so familiar to us. And you should be asking me this question right now.
How in the world does a shepherd keep sheep and goats alive in these kind of conditions?
And the answer is regular movement to find fresh pasturage.
So that means that our shepherds are regularly on the move.
They're heading north, south, and north again from Beersheba to Hebron to Jerusalem to Shechem and back again.
So our shepherds in the Bible are often isolated and isolated with hundreds of animals that they need to tend and defend.
From the dangers of predators, assisting with birth, treatment of injuries, disease, seeking out the scattered, watching out for thieves.
This is not an eight to five kind of job, and it is not an easy existence.
But the news is that this occupation of keeping flocks is literally as old as the hills in the ancient Near East.
Everyone in the world of the Bible, everyone knew what a shepherd was.
They knew what a shepherd did, they knew what a good shepherd looked like, and they knew what a bad shepherd looked like.
And in every era of Israelite history, our heroes were keeping sheep.
So the ideas of shepherd as leader and sheep as followers were already ancient by the time that Abraham, the shepherd, and Moses, the shepherd, and David, the shepherd, stepped onto the scene.
And did you know that this image is so embedded in the world of the ancient Near East that we can track it all the way back to the ancient Egyptians and the Mesopotamians, as far back as the third millennia BCE?
That means a thousand years before Abraham. What you're looking at right here is an image of Pharaoh's censurette, and what he has in his staff, in his hand, do you recognize it?
It's a shepherd's staff. And to his side, you're looking at the famous stela of Naram-Sin, the larger-than-life king of Akkad in 2200 BCE, 200 years before Abraham. And he, in this stela, is declaring himself the shepherd Naram-Sin.
Even Enlil, one of the great gods of the Mesopotamian pantheon, he called himself the shepherd of the black-headed people. Heck, the hieroglyph in Egyptian for leader, even though Egyptians don't like shepherds, is a shepherd's staff.
So what this means is that our heroes, the Israelites, they didn't think up the idea of shepherd as leader. They adopted it. Because shepherds lead. Shepherds protect. Shepherds provide. Specifically, they lead, protect, provide sheep. Yeah.
Now, to be more specific, as you look at these images, most of which I took actually, you are looking at mixed flocks of fat-tailed Awasi sheep and black Sinai goats. Take that one home over lunch, yeah? Okay.
You would have little flocks in the city, eight to ten. Huge flocks in the country, eight to ten thousand. These creatures were an everyday occurrence in the land of the Bible.
In every stage of Israel's history. So just like you can't travel 20 yards in our world without running into an iPhone or a car, you can't go 20 yards in their world without running into a sheep or a goat.
So this is why this image is so embedded in your Bible. And it's why it permeates our faith lives. Because these were the metaphors they lived by.
Yeah? And for the Bedouin who are still living on the margins of urban Israel and Jordan today, which is where these images come from, they still are.
Now I want you to notice specifically that you're not looking at just one kind of animal here. You're looking at two kinds of animals here from mixed flocks.
So these two are show animals, so they've been all cleaned up, and all of you 4-H people know exactly what I'm talking about.
And being all cleaned up, you are looking at the left at a black Sinai goat, and at the right you're looking at a fat-tailed awasi sheep.
Now why would you keep mixed flocks? In fact, the word for flock in Hebrew is sun, and it means them. That's what it means.
We have a few individual words, but we very rarely use them. Why a mixed flock? Well, it's kind of like a diversified portfolio.
Yeah? Sheep were more valuable, for sure. They're your stocks. But goats are more durable. They're your bonds.
Sheep, sheep can be super sensitive to heat and drought. They're picky eaters. They get lost easily. They're nearsighted. Did you know that?
Yeah? And are pretty much helpless in the face of a predator. And, well, they're not terribly bright.
I hate to tell you this. As this little video that Dave's about to play for us demonstrates brilliantly. Here we go.
Yeah, right there, that's my faith life. Okay.
So that's a sheep, yeah? Where, as a black Sinai goat, can survive just about anything.
They eat, for those of you who have goats, literally anything, and they have an extremely high tolerance to heat.
They only need to be watered once every four days in the high heat of summer. That's crazy!
And if you cook them very slowly, and you use the right spices, they can be quite tasty.
All right, so these would be your bonds. Our sheep, our stocks, our goats, bonds. That's what we've got.
Even when the market goes south, your goats don't. So, let's dive into the metaphor a little bit more.
You are looking at a picture of a very dear friend of mine, currently the Senior Vice President of Global Content
at our daily bread ministries. We went to Harvard together many, many moons ago.
And while on sabbatical leave from Gordon-Conwell Theological Seminary, and with a grant from the Albright Institute,
Tim packed up his journal and his canteen, and of course his faithful sidekick, that would be his son Jesse,
and he headed out into the wilderness of Jordan and Israel-Palestine to interview every Bedouin shepherd who would have him.
What was his goal? His goal was to understand the metaphor.
So first, Tim--well, the question, what did Tim learn? First, Tim learned that you can't find out how to be a shepherd from a book.
That's interesting. And all of you pastors in the room, even though I've been a seminary professor, this is true.
Rather, competence comes from a long-lived apprenticeship.
He learned that the wilderness can kill you. He learned that water is absolutely essential to life.
And a shepherd who does not know where to find the water will not be a shepherd for long.
Tim learned that adequate pasturage for your flock requires relentless effort.
And I think your pastors can say amen to that as well. North and south and then north again.
He learned that a shepherd is a midwife. That had not crossed my mind.
That successful births in the wilderness often require human intervention.
Injured and inexperienced ewes, they often panic in the birthing process.
And if shepherd doesn't step in and calm his ewe and assist in the emergence of the lamb, he's going to lose both of them.
Tim found out that it's not unusual for a shepherd to have to teach a ewe to accept her offspring.
Tim's Bedouin shepherd spoke of the lambing season as the, quote, "crisis of the shepherd's year."
The truest test of their commitment, stamina, and skill. What else did Tim learn?
Well, he learned that sheep need protection. Apparently, sheep, again, are terribly nearsighted.
They can't tell if that lump in front of them is a boulder or a wolf. Yeah? Who knew?
They get lost regularly. This is like a normal everyday occurrence, kind of like that gully.
And when they get lost, they panic. I don't know, pastors. I'm thinking. Yeah, I am.
So once they get lost and they panic, do you know what they do? They hunker down and they start crying,
which is a really effective way to find the nearest predator. Yeah?
And as sheep are not aggressive, they have no biting teeth or claws,
their only natural defense is to huddle. This reminds me of most every committee I have ever served on.
Their defense to a crisis? Quick! Huddle! That'll work. Yes, it will.
They're not smart. They smell. And aren't we the sheep of his hand? Hmm.
And shepherds do indeed call their sheep by name, and more surprising, the sheep come. Yeah.
So just as the wilderness, in addition, is a natural environment for flocks,
so it is too for wolves, and bears, and lions, and thieves.
So when we take all of this information and we put it into one sentence, here it is.
Sheep need shepherds. And without a shepherd, sheep become prey, and they die. Yeah.
Tim finally learned that in the world of sheep and shepherds, one lost sheep is a crisis.
It's a tragedy, and a tragedy that must be corrected.
So let me tell you a little story about a boy named Said.
Said was seven years old. Yeah? Seven years old, a little Bedouin boy from the Sinai.
And like many of his peers, by the age of seven, seven, he was being apprenticed into his father's trade.
So Said was regularly sent out with a little flock of 30 goats to shepherd for the day.
Well, one day, Said came home without a goat. There was one missing.
Apparently, he had been distracted by a particularly cute little shepherdess who had her 30 goats on the other side of the hill.
So his father's response to the situation was, as Tim declares, in our minds, swift and harsh.
The chief shepherd told his son, "You get back out there, and you find that goat, and you do not come home until you do."
And so, Said, seven years old, headed back to the mountain in the dark, in the cold, alone, and he searched for that missing goat for two days.
Now, guys, my kids, when they were seven years old, they didn't go in the backyard without supervision.
And this boy is out there for two days. Now, the goat was smart. Goats, they're difficult, but they are smart, yeah?
And so he figured out he was lost. He came home in time for the evening meal, yeah?
And of course, Said's father knew that. But Said's dad did not send anyone out to search for his son.
Rather, after two days, when the boy came home, hungry, empty-handed, frightened, embarrassed,
and when the boy realized that the goat had already returned and was perfectly safe,
there were no apologies from his father, and there was no attitude from the boy.
You see, everyone in Israel's world knew that the life of the flock, hear me on this,
is as important as the life of the shepherd. "What do you think?" Jesus asked.
"If a man owns a hundred sheep and one of them wanders away, will he not leave the ninety and nine
and go to look for the one that wandered off?" He's not blowing smoke.
So now that we know a little bit more about sheep and shepherds,
let's turn back to our psalm, written by David the shepherd. And how does it read?
"The Lord is my shepherd. I shall not want," is probably what you've memorized,
or "I lack nothing." Even better, with the commentator Kohler,
"So long as the Lord is my shepherd, I suffer no lack."
So let's pause and remember what we know about sheep for a minute.
What do sheep need? They need food. They're picky eaters in a desert region.
They need water daily. They need protection hourly. They need guidance.
They don't know where the water is. They need courage.
The kind of courage required to move from this space, hear me on this, that has become so comfortable,
but is quickly running out of the resources necessary to my survival, and I can't see that.
Sheep need help in the birthing process. If Canvas Community Church is going to reproduce,
they're not going to do it without the help of the Holy Spirit. Sheep don't reproduce without assistance.
Good shepherds, good shepherds provide all of these things, and sheep, well, we just sort of bob along,
expecting it all to happen, yeah? So what is our man David saying? Well, he's talking to himself, first of all.
He's talking to himself just the way I do when I'm praying, and he's speaking courage into his soul.
He's reminding himself that the limited resources that he sees are not the resources that the shepherd sees.
The Lord is my shepherd. I have everything I need. No, I do have everything I need. He makes me lie down in green pastures,
or in pasture lands that are full of tender grasses. He beds me down. You've seen the terrain, yeah?
You've seen what the land of Israel considered a pasture. And this psalm is being super specific,
that our shepherd does not rest until he finds pastures that are full of desha,
is the Hebrew word, grass. And until he's convinced that his wandering nearsighted flock is safe,
and he's convinced that wandering nearsighted flock not to stop until they are. He beds me down. In other words,
at the end of the day, when the darkness is falling, and the predators are emerging from their dens,
my good shepherd makes sure that I'm in a good place, a safe place, even a comfortable place.
I don't deserve that. I don't know about you. He leads me beside quiet waters,
which can also be translated well-watered pasturage. He restores my soul.
Now again, you've seen what the normal state of affairs is with water in the land of Israel.
And water is not a garden hose away in these lands of pasturage.
It only rains in the wintertime. That's like once every six months.
And wells and cisterns were fiercely guarded in this world.
For those under 35, think dune. You got it. Okay.
So this shepherd knows his trade. He knows when and where to pasture his
flock. He knows where the water is. He restores my soul.
Literally, he causes my life to return to me.
Causes my life to return to me. I'm going to be okay.
He leads me in paths of righteousness for his namesake.
Now this phrase literally means well-worn, even entrenched.
The kind of path that is used so often that when the rains hit, it becomes a water gully.
This is the kind of path that the people who know where they're going,
actually use.
And they don't need any help from the most recent Instagram reel on howtomakeyourlifebetter.com.
Yeah?
Because this shepherd knows what he's doing.
He knows where he needs to lead his flock to keep them safe.
And why is he doing it?
For his name's sake.
Do you know that the word name is an ancient idiom for reputation?
And do you know that your God, the creator of the universe, has chosen that his most significant testimony to his own character is you.
Is you.
So even when I walk in the valley of Tzalmaveth, that's the Hebrew term.
Some of your Bibles translate that the shadow of death. Some as the darkest valley.
There's been a huge linguistic debate on that translation. Is this indeed the vernacular idea of the shadow of death, kind of a mythological place that terrifies everyone?
Or is it that deep, dark ravine where a pack of wolves could easily isolate and devastate the flock? Which one is it?
Well, the debate right now is move back to that dark mythological place that we're all terrified of.
The shadow of death. Which in our vernacular would be, "Even though I walk through hell itself, I will fear no evil."
Can I say statistically with the number of people in this room that there are at least a handful of you who right now, right here, are walking through the valley of the shadow of death.
And first of all, I'm so sorry. You feel threatened, vulnerable, frightened. You don't think you're going to make it through this.
But your psalmist is telling you to hang in there. And why are you going to hang in there? Because we have a good shepherd.
He's got a firm hold on that staff, and he's leading the way. He has demonstrated a thousand times, day in and day out, that he will defend us.
No predator is going to find you in this dark valley, not on his watch, because you are not alone.
And I don't know about you, but I can handle just about anything if somebody I trust is standing next to me.
Your rod and your staff, they comfort me. That rod is a weapon, by the way. What did George Adam Smith say to us? On some high moor across which the night
hyenas howl, when you meet him, sleepless, farsighted, not nearsighted, weather-beaten, armed, leaning on his staff.
Can I tell you that I have seen enough battles and trials and dangers that I have been deeply grateful that my shepherd is not only kind, but he's armed and he's dangerous.
And he has defended me more than once. My shepherd is brave. My shepherd is strong. My shepherd is wise. And I'm going to be okay.
That was David's declaration. That was David's prayer. And it has been given to us 3,000 years later in the words of Athanasius to pray for us.
You see, David knew what it was to be a sheep. He knew what it was to be nearsighted, defenseless, confused, a prey animal. But he also knew it would be a shepherd.
The one force that stands between me and that predator. And in this case, and this moment, the moment of Psalm 23, David the sheep needed a shepherd.
And so David the sheep is reciting the Psalm of confidence for himself and for us. And can I tell you that this idea of sheep and shepherd did not get retired into the Disney vault with Psalm 23?
Yeah? Rather, when God calls David to kingship, he tells him to shepherd my people Israel. Do you hear it? Shepherd my people Israel.
So when we get to Psalm 78, David is celebrated as the one who would shepherd my people Jacob according to the integrity of his heart, and with skillful hands, he guides and leads them.
And when the kingdom collapses and the exile commence, and the prophet Ezekiel blames the great collapse of the kingdom, who does he blame it on?
He blames it on irresponsible shepherds. He speaks of how they protected their own concerns and their own comfort, not the well-being of the flock.
And so we read, "Woe to the shepherds of Israel, who only take care of themselves. Should not a shepherd take care of the flock?
You eat the curds, you clothe yourselves with wool, you slaughter the choice animals, but you don't take care of my flock.
You've not strengthened the weak, or healed the sick, or bound up the injured."
That literally says "shattered ones."
In other words, an animal with a broken leg that a shepherd doesn't care enough to splint. Yeah?
No, my people have been scattered because there was no shepherd, and they became prey for all the wild animals.
My sheep were scattered over the whole earth, and no one went out to search for them.
Can I tell you that when the exile happened, hear me on this,
when Jerusalem was burned to the ground, when the temple was pulled down stone by stone,
that everyone, from the surviving King Jehoiakim, the last of David's line, to the common man on the street,
everyone thought it was over. Over. We've gone too far.
We've broken trust too many times. He's gone. We're gone. It's done.
Ever been there? But the New Testament has a different story to tell.
Luke 19: "For the Son of Man came to seek and save the lost, who have been scattered over every high hill."
Matthew 10:6 says, "Jesus, speaking to his disciples, I want you to go to the lost sheep of Israel."
And then we get to John. And here, Jesus, the son of David, tells us he is the good shepherd, and the good shepherd lays down his life for his sheep.
You see, the hired hand, he's not the shepherd, and he doesn't own the sheep.
So when he sees the wolf coming, he abandons the sheep, he runs away. And then the wolf attacks the flock and he scatters it.
That man runs away because he's a hired hand and because he cares nothing for the sheep.
But me? I'm the good shepherd. I know my sheep. And my sheep know me. And I lay down my life for the sheep.
That's who I am. That's what I do. So brothers and sisters, be encouraged.
Because the Lord God, the King of the universe, the Creator of heaven and earth, He is your shepherd.
You have everything you need. And how does Psalm 23 end? Well, after shifting its metaphor to a gracious host who welcomes the outsider with royal extravagance,
your psalmist ends with this statement, "Surely His goodness and love," that's chesed, by the way, "His covenant faithfulness,"
"will follow me all the days of my life." Can I tell you that the Hebrew doesn't simply say, "Follow me."
It actually uses the verb radath, which is exactly the verb you use when a wolf is chasing down a sheep.
His goodness, His mercy will chase me down all the days of my life, just like those wolves who stalk in the ravines with murderous intent,
or the enemies who are outraged that I'm sitting at the king's table. Your God has not simply vowed to protect you
from the forces that seek to injure you. Your God has turned the equation upside down. All the days of my life,
I will dwell in the Bet Av, the house of the Lord forever. So be of good courage. Be of good courage. Your shepherd
is leading you on the right path. Before this is over, you're going to be bedded down in watered spaces.
He knows what he's doing, and you are going to come out of this on the other side. And if today you find
yourself in the shadow of death, well, don't be afraid. You're not alone. Your God is looking out over
the flock, and he's saying, "You see that one? She's mine." And like all good shepherds, this one is
willing to lay down his life for his sheep. In the name of the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
Amen, amen, amen.